中文字幕｜沉默中的爆发 [自翻]
英文字幕｜CheungCheung [来源网络]
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
海 蒂 和 爷 爷
海蒂！过来！
Heidi! Come on!
你好，迪提
Hello, Dete.
好热
I'm hot.
- 还有多远？ - 海蒂，就在山顶
- Is it far?  - Heidi, it's right at the top.
你好，迪提
Hello, Dete.
你好
Hello.
- 这是你妹妹的女儿？ - 是的
- Is that your late sister's daughter?  - Yes.
- 过来，海蒂，我们要走了  - 她都长这么大了
- Come on, Heidi. We have to go.  - She's got so big.
过来
Come on.
你要带她去哪？
Where are you taking her?
- 到她爷爷那去  - 去阿蒙治叔叔那？
- To her grandfather.  - To the Alp-Uncle?
我的老天！
Good heavens!
迪提
Dete.
他很冷漠讨厌与人接触
He's godless and hates every living soul.
据说他甚至忘记了怎么说话
They say he even forgot how to speak.
我要把她寄养在别人家？
Am I meant to put her in a home?
或者把她交给我们不认识的农民家？
Or give her to some farmer we don't know?
你应当明白没有人想多养活一个人
You know that nobody wants an extra mouth to feed.
同陌生人呆在一起也许对她比较好
She might have been better off with strangers.
他甚至与自己的儿子闹翻了，愿上帝宽恕他的灵魂
He even fell out with his own son. May God rest his soul.
同时我确定他不会想和这个孩子扯上关系
And I'm sure he won't want anything to do with the child.
海蒂！你在哪？
Heidi! Where are you?
海蒂，马上过来
Heidi, come here right now!
过来！
Coming!
你好，爷爷
Hello, Grandfather.
你好，阿蒙治叔叔
Hello, Alp-Uncle.
她叫海蒂
This is Heidi.
你的孙女
Your grandchild.
我在法兰克福找到份工作
I've found a position in Frankfurt.
所以我把她带给你
So now I'm bringing her to you.
她毕竟流淌着你的血脉
She's your own flesh and blood after all.
带着她滚
Go! And take her with you.
我已经照顾她五年了
I've looked after her for five years.
- 现在没法照顾了  - 滚！
- But I can't do it anymore.  - Get out of here!
海蒂，听好了
Heidi, listen to me.
没有什么好害怕的
There's nothing to be scared of.
我确定你爷爷不会伤害你
I'm sure Uncle won't hurt you.
好的，过去吧
Right, now go.
去啊！
Go!
上帝原谅我吧
God forgive me.
孩子！把这孩子带走！
The child!Take the child with you!
过来，跟她走！
Go on, go with her!
她不要我了
But she doesn't want me either.
爷爷？
Grandfather?
早上好，爷爷
Good morning, Grandfather.
喝吧
Drink.
- 谢谢  - 我带你去牧师那一趟
- Thank you.  - I'll take you to the parson.
他会知道怎么处理你
He'll know what to do with you.
张嘴
Open up.
孩子很结实
The child is strong.
健康
And healthy.
她不会有问题的
She won't be much trouble.
她不能和我呆在一起
She can't stay with me.
好吧
Okay, fine.
- 这几天我要去迈恩费尔德一趟  - 也许有人可以收留她
- I'm going to Maienfeld in three days.  - Maybe a farmer has a use for her.
毕竟，是个家
Otherwise, it's a home.
但是她这段时间得和你住在一起
But she has to stay with you until then.
到时我带她过来
I'll bring her down then.
照顾你的孙女是你应尽的责任
It's your Christian duty to look after your grandchild.
好了，下来吧
Here, off you go.
爷爷？
Grandfather?
今晚我还睡在畜棚里吗？
Should I sleep in the stable again tonight?
随你睡哪儿
Sleep wherever you want.
你只有一把椅子
You only have one chair.
一张床
And only one bed.
上面是干什么的
What's that up there?
我想睡在上面的干草里，可以吗？
I want to sleep up here in the hay.Am I allowed?
爷爷？
Grandfather?
我不想去别人家
I'd rather not go into a home.
- 早上好，爷爷  - 喝你的牛奶
- Good morning, Grandfather.  - Drink your milk.
停下！
Stop there!  -
早上好，山羊们
Good morning, goats.  -
小熊、小天鹅[羊名]，过来！
Little Bear! Little Swan! Come on!
来吧
Come on! Chop chop!
早上好，牧羊人
Good day, General Goatherd.
今天带女孩和你一起去阿尔卑斯山上去
Take the girl with you out on the alp today.
她不知道山上的事情
She doesn't know how things work in the mountains.
你好，我叫海蒂
Hello. My name is Heidi.
- 好吧  - 谢谢
- Right.  - Thank you.
过来
Come on.
听到他说的了吗？你得听我的话
Did you hear him?You have to do what I say.
好的
Yeah, yeah.
- 你叫什么名字？ - 皮特
- What's your name?  - Peter.
- 你和他一起住吗？ - 是的，他是我爷爷
- Are you living with him now?  - Yes, he's my grandfather.
你爷爷？
Your grandfather?
为什么不和你的父母一起住
Why don't you live with your parents?
他们去世了
Because they're dead.
我父亲也去世了
My father is dead too.
以前我和我的姑姑迪提一起住在拉格斯
I was living with my Aunt Dete in Bad Ragaz until now.
一整天我都得坐在家里
I had to sit inside all day.
这里太好了，我可以出来玩！
But here is much better.I can be outside!
- 跟紧我  - 好的
- Hey, stay with me!  - Yeah, yeah.
那个小的叫什么？
What's that little one called?
- Snowhopper  - 你能教我怎么生火吗？
- Snowhopper.  - Will you show me how to make a fire?
当然可以
Sure.
嘿！皮特
Hey, Peter.
你吃了我的奶酪和香肠吗？
Did you eat some of my cheese and sausage?
什么，我吗？
What, me?
不，不是我
No, that wasn't me.
还能是谁？
Who else could it have been?
不知道，也许是山羊干的？
I don't know. Maybe a goat?
山羊？
A goat?
停下！
Hey! Stay there.
小天鹅，停下
Little Swan, Thistlefinch! Stop it, stop!
走开，停止打斗
Get away! Stop that!
- 待在那里  - 放过他
- Just you wait!  - Leave him!
没听见吗，我让你待在那里
Do you never listen?I said stay over there!
不要打它，它们不打架了
Stop hitting them!They stopped fighting.
需要惩罚它们，因为打架导致产奶少了
They need to be punished.They give less milk if they fight.
如果你不打它们，我分一半吃的给你
If you stop hitting them,I'll give you half my food.
一半？
Half of it?
每天？
Every day?
但你不能再打这些山羊
But you're not allowed to hit the goats anymore.
成交？
Do you promise?
每天，一半
Every day. Half.
- 看到了吗？ - 看到了
- Do you see? Look.  - I can see.
看，快，趴下
Look. Ouick, get down!
该你了
Now your turn.
- 我  - 是的
- Me?  - Yes.
- 海蒂？ - 嗯？
- Heidi?  - Yes?
- 不要提食物的事情  - 我不会说的
- Maybe don't mention the food.  - I won't say anything.
村里人说他杀过人
In the village they say he killed someone once.
谢谢
Thank you.
我还是睡在畜棚里吧
I'd rather sleep in the stable affer all.
皮特和你讲了我的传闻吗？
Did Peter tell you stories about me?
你相信他的话？
And you just believe him?
他说的是真的吗？
Is it true what he says?
人们喜欢说些鸡毛蒜皮的事情
People like saying nasty things.
你需要决定相信自己的眼睛和耳朵
You have to decide whether to trust your own eyes and ears
还是别人的话
or what other people say.
晚安，爷爷
Goodnight, Grandfather.
好美
Lovely.
我对这里很熟
I know my way around up here.
明天我告诉你雪绒花长在哪
I'll show you tomorrow where the edelweiss grows.
皮特
Peter.
明天我得走了，爷爷要带我去牧师那里
I'll be gone tomorrow.Grandfather is taking me to the parson.
什么？
What?
其实是舍不得那些吃的了吧！…^_^
我又要独自和这些愚蠢的山羊呆在一起了
I'm on my own with these stupid goats again.
走开
Shoo! Move! Come on.
Go! Move it!
看你弄成什么样了
What on earth do you look like?
爷爷？
Grandfather?
这是我的椅子？
Is the chair for me?
还能是谁的
Who else?
但我明天要离开了啊
But I'm leaving tomorrow.
你明天要去山上
You're going out on the alp tomorrow.
后天也去？
And the next day too?
当然
Certainly.
不要再问问题了，去洗干净你的脸
Don't ask so many questions and go and wash your face.
谢谢，谢谢，太感谢你了
Thank you, thank you, thank you!
皮特，我能留下来了
Peter! I'm allowed to stay!
- 今天是我最后一天来了  - 为什么
- Today is the last day I'll be here.  - Why?
我得去上学
I have to go to school.
什么时候回来？
When are you coming back?
春天吧，我想
In the spring, I think.
直到春天？
Not until the spring?
你可以下山到我家来
You can come down and visit.
我奶奶会很高兴看见你
Grandmother will be pleased to see you.
别吃了，吃的够多了
No more eating, you've had enough!
跟上！
Come on!
我能去上学吗？
May I go to school too?
过来，吃饭
Come on, eat.
看谁来了
Look who's there.
难以置信
That's unbelievable.
他不应该被允许照顾孩子
He shouldn't be allowed to take care of a child.
他看过来啦
He's looking over.
早上好
Good day.
你好
Hello.
阿蒙治叔叔…
Alp-Uncle...
对这个女孩你有什么规划
What do you have planned for the girl?
和你没关系
That's nothing to do with you.
她应该去上学
In a year she'll have to go to school.
她不需要
She doesn't have to do anything.
讲点理，每个孩子都该读书
Be sensible.Every child must learn to read.
她没法在冬天里独自一人从山上下来
She can't come down from the alp on her own in the winter.
过来，孩子，出去玩
Come on, child.You go outside.
整个冬天独自一人呆在山上
Alone the whole winter,up on that alp.
- 这么大的孩子需要朋友  - 她应有尽有
- A child of that age needs friends.  - She has all she needs.
这是违法的
It's against the law.
对你的法律不感兴趣
I'm not interested in your laws.
过来
Come on.
老顽固
Such a pig-headed fellow.
看
Here, look.
做好了
It's finished.
好漂亮
Beautiful.
谢谢你，爷爷
Thank you, Grandfather.
要是春天来了就好了
If only it were spring again.
快
Faster!
谢谢
Thank you.
天黑后我会来接你
When it gets dark,I'll come and pick you up.
皮特在家吗？
Hello, is Peter there?
他在学校，进来吧
He's at school.But come inside.
母亲，我们有客人来了，是海蒂
Mother, we have a visitor.It's Heidi.
你好
Hello.
孩子，她看不见
Child, she can't see.
靠近点，海蒂
Come a little closer, Heidi.
奶奶，你什么都看不见吗？
Can you see nothing, Grandmother?
是看不见
With my eyes, nothing at all.
但可以用手感受世界
But with my hands,it's different.
- 海蒂  - 皮特
- Heidi!  - Peter!
谢谢
Thank you.
你什么也没错过，学校好无聊
You're not missing anything.School is so boring.
你这样说是因为你不会读书
You just say that because you still can't read.
你也不会，读书有什么好的
You can't either.What good does reading do up here?
吃你的饭
Eat your food!
奶奶，吃我的吧
You can have mine, Grandmother.
谢谢，海蒂，它太硬了
Thank you, Heidi,but it's too hard.
我快没牙了
I hardly have any teeth left, you know.
那我给我吧
Then I'll take it.
奶奶看不见，你知道吗？
Grandmother can't see.Did you know?
她也不能吃陈面包
And she can't eat any stale bread at all.
我们很幸运，不是吗，爷爷
We're lucky, aren't we Grandfather?
噢，那里
Whoa there!
叔叔？你好
Uncle? Hello.
我带来一些好消息
I've got some good news.
我帮海蒂找到了好人家
I've found a place for Heidi,
在法兰克福，我雇主的朋友家里
with friends of my employers,in Frankfurt.
这是一个受人尊敬的家庭
It's a well-respected family,
海蒂可以和她们的女儿一起去上学
and Heidi could even go to school with their young daughter.
对她来说太好了
It's a wonderful chance for her.
说句话吧
Say something at least!
说完了就滚
When you're finished, you can go.
我想带走她
But I want to take her with me.
海蒂待在这里
Heidi is staying here.
村里人说你不让她上学
In the village they sayyou don't let her go to school.
因为你的固执她不会读也不会写
Because of your obstinacy,she won't learn to read or write!
你想让她在这里粗野下去？
You want her to turn wild up here?
你为什么突然这么关心她？
Why do you care about her all of a sudden?
叔叔，上次我也没办法
Uncle, last time I had no other choice.
没什么好说的了
There's nothing more to say.
如果你不让她上学
If you don't let her go to school,
他们会带走她并把她送到别人家里
they'll take her away from you and put her in a home.
我今天要带走她，如果需要的话会寻求村民的帮助
I'm taking her today. With help from the villagers, if needs be.
孩子在哪？
Where is the child?
海蒂是我的
Heidi is mine.
现在滚！
Now get out of here.
- 海蒂  - 迪提？
- Heidi!  - Dete?
- 迪提姑姑  - 海蒂，我的孩子
- Aunt Dete!  - Heidi, my child.
过来
Come here.
想我吗？
Have you missed me lots?
小孩，放你的羊去
Boy, go back to your goats.
我和海蒂有话要说
I have to talk to Heidi.Come on.
坐下
Sit down.
听我说
Listen to me.
你想住在一个又大又漂亮的房子里吗？
How would you like to live in a big, beautiful house?
泽塞曼一家，来自法兰克福的非常好的人
The Sesemanns,very kind people from Frankfurt,
正在为他们的女儿寻找朋友
are looking for a friend for their daughter.
但我喜欢这里
But I like it here.
但是法兰克福的女孩期待你的到来
But the girl in Frankfurt is so looking forward to you coming.
我还是想和爷爷待在一起
I'd rather stay with Grandfather.
海蒂，爷爷让你和我一起走
Heidi, Grandfather wants you to come with me.
真的？
Really?
孩子，我们都希望把最好的给你
Child, we both just want what is best for you.
过来，火车快要开了
Come along.The train is leaving soon.
- 但我得说再见  - 没时间了
- But I have to say goodbye.  - We don't have any time.
- 远吗？ - 不远
- Is it far away?  - No, no.
如果我不喜欢那里呢
And what if I don't like it?
你可以回来
Then you can come back home.
我保证
I promise.
跟上
Come on.
过来，快点
Come on, hurry!
海蒂在哪
Where is Heidi?
快点
Go, hurry!
上来
Hop on.
- 出发吧  - 好的
- Off we go!  - All right.
他们走了，你又晚了，不是吗？
They've gone!You're late again, aren't you?
一直在寻找
Keep looking.
孩子还活着真是一个奇迹
It's a miracle the child is still alive.
海蒂，待在这
Heidi, stay here.
待在这
Stay here!
海蒂，和我来，跟上
Heidi, come with me.Come inside.
有空吗
Are you free?
请去泽塞曼家
The Sesemann mansion, please.
过来
Come on.
海蒂
Heidi!
出来
Get out.
- 日安，女士  - 日安
- Good day, ladies.  - Good day.
欢迎，女士
Welcome, ladies.
洛特梅尔小姐正在等我们
Miss Rottenmeier is waiting for us.
请跟着我
Please follow me.
海蒂，住手
Heidi, stop it!
现在我要向洛特梅尔小姐介绍你，好吗？
I'm introducing you to Miss Rottenmeier now, okay?
她是年轻小姐的家庭教师
That's the young lady's governess.
家庭教师？
Governess?
她是一位非常优秀的女士，现在照顾克拉拉小姐
She's a very distinguished woman who looks affer Miss Klara.
好好表现
So behave yourself!
- 洛特梅尔小姐等着见你们  - 好的，跟上
- Miss Rottenmeier will see you now.  - Right. Come along.
不幸的是，我没时间给她换衣服
Unfortunately, I had no time to change her clothes.
- 你叫什么名字？ - 海蒂
- What is your name?  - Heidi.
海蒂？那不是一个基督徒的名字
Heidi? That's not a Christian name.
她叫艾迪尔海德，像她母亲
Her name is Adelheid, like her mother.
上帝保佑她的灵魂
God rest her soul.
孩子在我看来太小
The child seems very young to me.
确实，对于她的年纪来说身体有点小
Indeed, she is quite small for her age.
- 我八岁了  - 八岁
- I'm eight.  - Eight.
不，这还不够，跟我过来，迪提
No, that won't do at all.Come with me, Dete.
艾迪尔海德正是泽塞曼先生需要的
Adelheid is exactly what Mr Sesemann wanted.
来自瑞士乡下的孩子
An unspoiled child from the Swiss countryside.
现在给我的报酬吧
And now I want my side of the deal.
- 我该叫你什么？ - 海蒂
- What should I call you?  - Heidi.
我是克拉拉
I'm Klara.
来法兰克福开心吗
Were you excited about Frankfurt?
爷爷和迪提姑姑希望我来
Grandfather and Aunt Dete wanted me to come,
但如果我不喜欢，我可以回去
but if I don't like it, I'm allowed to go back home.
你是我见过最好奇的孩子
You're the most curious girl I've ever met.
这是男孩子的衣服吗
Are those boys' clothes?
在阿尔卑斯山区这很常见，尤其适合攀爬
It's practical on the alp.Especially for climbing.
噢，攀爬
Oh, climbing...
你不能走路吗？
Can't you walk?
很不幸，不能
No, sadly not.
- 所以你得坐在这上面？ - 是的
- So you always have to sit in this?  - Yes.
随便推我走走吧
Feel free to push me.
喜欢我们的房子吗
How do you like our house?
好大
It's big.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
怎么了
What happened?
我冲向了桌子，没注意，抱歉
I rode into the table. I wasn't paying attention. I'm sorry.
好吧，晚饭时间到了
Right. It's time for supper.
坐吧
Let's sit.
你看起来像皮特一样的牧羊人
You look a bit like Peter the goatherd.
- 请原谅  - 什么？
- Adelheid.  - Adelheid
不要那样和仆人交谈
Don't talk like that to the servants.
这间房子里我们用餐具
In this house we use cutlery.
她不知道这些常识
She doesn't even know the very basics.
抱歉，我去拿抹布
Sorry. I'll get a rag.
抹布？
A rag?
坐下，艾迪尔海德！
Sit down, Adelheid!
蒂妮特，安静
Tinette. Silence!
能给我两个吗？
Can I have two?
塞巴斯蒂安
Sebastian.
纠正发音的问题
他能给我两个面包卷吗？
"Can he please pass me two rolls?"
他能给…我两个面包卷吗？
Can he please... give me two rolls?
递给我两个面包卷
"Pass me two rolls."
Pass me two rolls.
两卷
Two rolls.
两卷，请
Two rolls, please.
艾迪尔海德，在这房子里有些规矩
In this house there are rules, Adelheid.
提到仆人时你要说他或者她
You are to refer to the servants as 'he' or 'she',
禁止与他们交谈
and conversing with them is forbidden.
早餐是七点半
Breakfast is at 7:30.
八点十五分开始上课
Lessons will take place in the study and commence at 8:15.
十二点半午餐
At 12:30 we take our lunch.
两小时午休
Then two hours of rest.
晚上七点上床睡觉
At 7 it's bed time.
房间里禁止奔跑，跳跃
In this house there is no running, hopping or jumping.
我们一直步行
We always walk.
从不大声说话
We never raise our voices.
洛特梅尔小姐？
Miss Rottenmeier?
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
你不能像这样来回奔跑
You can't run around here like that.
- 我？ - 是的！
- Me?  - Yes!
山上的人都不洗澡吗？
Don't people wash up in the mountains?
不，我们洗
Yes, we do.
我听说在山上
I have heard that up there,
有巨人和侏儒
there are mountain trolls and gnomes.
你见过吗？
Have you ever seen one?
别动
Stay still.
穿上鞋子，准备好的话就上楼
Now put those on, and when you're ready, come upstairs.
海蒂
Heidi!
不，黄油刀
No, the butter knife.
好的，艾迪尔海德小姐
Okay, Miss Adelheid.
打开书本至第一章并朗读
Open the book at chapter one and read aloud.
我不会
I can't.
什么？
Pardon?
我不会读
I can't read.
你应该认识字母
You must know the letters.
这是哪个字母？
Which letter is this?
看起来像是座山
It's like a mountain.
是的，它是
Yes, it is.
克拉拉小姐，这不好笑
Miss Klara, this is not funny.
皮特也不会读书
Peter can't read either.
- 皮特？ - 皮特？
- Peter?  - Peter?
他是我的朋友
He's my friend.
皮特说我们山上不需要这个
Peter said we don't need to up on the alp.
不需要？
You don't need to?
小姐…
Miss...
每个人都应该也必须学会朗读
Every person can and must learn to read.
失陪一会
Please excuse me one moment.
她不认识字母表？
She doesn't know the alphabet?
粗野没教养的家伙不应该带进我们的房子
A completely wild, uneducated creature has been brought into our house.
也许她应该有个单独的老师
Maybe it would be appropriate for her to have a separate teacher.
你这么想？
You'd like that.
不可能在进行克拉拉小姐
It can't be asking too much
的课程时同时教这个瑞士孩子字母表
to teach the Swiss child the alphabet alongside Klara's lesson.
当然不行，我只是想
Certainly not, I just thought...
一旦泽塞曼先生回来，我相信艾迪尔海德得离开这里
As soon as Mr Sesemann returns, I'll ensure Adelheid leaves this house.
窗户打不开吗？
Doesn't this window open?
为什么？
Why?
我想试试看能否看到大山
I want to find out if you can see the mountains.
艾迪尔海德小姐，能回到自己的座位吗？
Miss Adelheid, would you be so kind as to retake your seat
这样我们可以继续我们的课程
so that we can continue with the much-needed lesson?
克拉拉小姐
Miss Klara.
艾迪尔海德小姐，这个山叫做A
Miss Adelheid, the mountain is called 'A'.
艾迪尔海德的A
'A' for Adelheid.
- 对  - “A”
- Exactly.  - 'A'.
推我过去，海蒂
Take me over there, Heidi.
不要拉开这么大，不要被人发现
Not so wide! We don't want to be seen.
我想让你看看这个
I wanted to show you this.
- 是你吗？ - 和我的母亲一起
- Is that you?  - And my mother.
但是你是站立的
But you're standing up.
是的
Yes.
我生病了在
I only became ill affer...
我母亲去世后
Affer she died.
父亲也想她
Father misses her too.
他经常因工作出去
He's always travelling for his work.
我一直被困在这间房子里
And I'm always stuck in this house.
你！
You!
上帝啊，年轻女士不会这样悄悄移动
Goodness me! Young ladies don't creep up like that.
抱歉
Sorry.
现在是午休时间，艾迪尔海德小姐
It's nap time, Miss Adelheid.
我睡不着
But I can't sleep.
不是睡觉，只是休息
You shouldn't sleep, just rest.
需要我做些什么，年轻的女士
How can I be of service to the young lady?
你能
Do you...
他知道怎样打开窗户吗
Does he know how to open the window?
哪一扇
Which one?
好了，小姐[法语]
Here, mademoiselle.
小心，不要这么远
Good gracious, not so far!
根本看不见山
There are no mountains at all.
好吧，从这里你不会看见任何山
Well, you can't see any from up here,
但是，看，在那个塔上你能看的更远
but look,you can see much further from the tower.
现在我得关上窗户，年轻的女士得回她的房间
But now I have to close the window again and the young lady goes to her room.
否则会有麻烦了
Otherwise there'll be trouble.
谢谢你，再见
Thank you and adieu.
再见
Adieu.
我们得在午休结束前回来
We have to be back before the afternoon rest is over.
当然
Sure.
右边
Right.
不，左边
No, left!
对了，这边
That's right. Along there.
苹果，新鲜的苹果
Apples, fresh apples!
新鲜的苹果
Fresh apples!
塔
The tower.
现在在哪儿？
Where is it now?
海蒂，我不知道
Heidi, I don't know right now.
也许他知道
Maybe he knows.
海蒂，你不能同乞丐说话
Heidi, you can't talk to a beggar!
海蒂
Heidi!
这边
This way.
就在那儿
There it is.
面包，新鲜的面包
Bread! Fresh bread!
新鲜的面包
Fresh bread!
这儿，从这里进去吧
There. That's where you go in.
你呢？
What about you?
别管我，快上去
Don't worry about me. Go on, hurry!
去
Go!
我希望小姐休息好了
I hope miss is well rested.
小姐？
Miss?
我想年轻的女士会喜欢这个
I'm sure the young lady will like this.
好可爱
How cute.
只花一点点钱
If you have a few pennies...
不要站在那儿，去找
Don't just stand there. Search!
小姐？
Miss?
艾迪尔海德
Adelheid!
克拉拉
Klara!
找不到他们
I can't find them.
前门开着
The front door was open.
- 然后呢？ - 也许她们出去了
- And?  - Maybe they went out.
好吧，为什么出去，去哪儿了？
Oh, right. Why out? Where?
我想我们得出去找她们
I think we should look for them outside.
天啊
Good God!
塞巴斯蒂安，找到那些孩子
Find the children, Sebastian.
找到她们
Find them!
山在哪儿？
Where are the mountains?
爷爷
Grandfather.
海蒂，怎么样了？
Heidi, how was it?
卢克
Look.
它们好可爱
They're so sweet.
我们得走了
We have to go.
快点
Come on!
小姐
Miss!
你在干什么
What do you think you're doing?
尽快回去
Back to the house, quick as you can.
她们到底去哪了
Where on earth were they?
不远，她们只是想去
Not far.They just wanted to...
- 呼吸点新鲜空气  - 对
- Get some fresh air.  - Exactly.
你把克拉拉带出了这间屋子
You took Klara out of this house.
你知道这有多危险吗？
Are you aware of how dangerous that is?
什么
What...
如果出了什么事怎么和她父亲交代
What would you have told her father if something had happened to her?
你的腰带…
And your sash is all...
天啊，这些小东西必须出去
Oh, goodness! Those creatures must go.
- 不！  - 塞巴斯蒂安
- No...  - Sebastian!
- 不能留下它们吗？ - 当然不行
- Can't we keep them?  - Absolutely not!
我…
I...
我无法呼吸，猫毛
I can't breathe. The fur!
天啊
Oh God!
弄走它们
Get them away!
这些东西必须弄走
Those creatures must go!
快点，塞巴斯蒂安
Hurry up. Ouickly, Sebastian!
- 我会照顾这些小东西  - 我无法呼吸
- I'll look affer these little mites.  - I can't breathe.
天啊，抓住那里的那只，快
Oh my god, take that one there!Hurry up!
塞巴斯蒂安，我的天
Sebastian! Oh God.
塞巴斯蒂安，猫，它在攻击我
Sebastian! The cat! It's attacking me!
不
No.
艾迪尔海德今晚没有晚饭吃
Adelheid will have no supper this evening.
- 但…  - 泽塞曼小姐
- But...  - Miss Sesemann.
改由大人们来决定怎样抚养小孩
It is for adults to decide how children are brought up.
站在那里
Stand over there.
面对墙壁
With your face to the wall.
动起来
Get a move on!
面对墙壁
With your face to the wall.
面对墙壁，我说了
With your face to the wall, I said!
下次我会把你和老鼠一起关在笼子里
Next time I'll lock you in the cellar with the rats.
我要回家
I have to go home.
什么？
Pardon me?
What?
海蒂
Heidi!
我只是想
I just have to.
但是…
But...
- 但是为什么，海蒂  - 艾迪尔海德
- But why? Heidi!  - Adelheid
停在那儿
Stop right there.
海蒂，等等
Heidi, wait!
- 我说了停下  - 海蒂
- I said stop!  - Heidi!
不要走
Don't go!
你怎么敢
How dare you!
迪提说了我可以随时离开
Dete said I can leave when I want.
她说了吗？
Did she really?
她骗了你，你无法离开
Then she lied. There's no way you're leaving.
你难道不知道你有多幸运吗
Don't you know how lucky you are?
我多么希望我在这样的家庭长大
I wish I had grown up in such a house.
带这么多面包卷你想干什么
What did you want to do with those rolls?
为了奶奶
They're for Grandmother.
愚蠢的孩子
You stupid child.
丢下它们
Leave them there.
海蒂，你在干什么
Heidi, what are you doing?
瞧你对千金小姐做了什么
Look what you're doing to the young lady.
回你的房间
Now go to your room.
现在
Right this second.
蒂妮特
Tinette.
Tinette!
爷爷
Grandfather.
克拉拉在哪
Where is Klara?
她病了
She's ill.
病了，都怪你
Sick! Because of you.
哦，我们的小瑞士女孩来了
So, here's our little Swiss girl.
不要害怕，我只是个医生
Don't be scared. I'm just the doctor.
- 嗨  - 嗨？
- Hiya.  - Hiya?
嗨
Hiya.
克拉拉病了吗
Is Klara sick?
她现在好多了
The young lady is much better.
我想她会很高兴见到你
I think she'll be pleased to see you.
再见
Goodbye.
Adieu.
我是如此的糟糕以至于你想离开吗
Am I so awful I make you want to leave?
不，不是因为那个
No, that's not it.
我只有你，海蒂
I only have you, Heidi.
我们能够一起度过一段美好时光
We could have such a nice time together.
“N”！
'N'.
- 你现在应该快点  - “O”
- You should be a little faster by now.  - 'O'.
看起来像面包卷
It looks like a bread roll.
确实像
Exactly.
它不是“tread”的“T”
It's not a 'T' for tread,
或者“kread”的“K”
or a 'K' for kread,
只是个“B…bread”的“B”
but a 'B'... A 'B' for bread.
以一个“B”开始
And that starts with a...
你到底怎么了，你忘了吗？
'B'! What's wrong with you? How have you forgotten?
你打扮的真漂亮
You've really dolled yourself up.
我根本没有打扮自己，你怎敢[这样说]！
I haven't dolled myself up at all. How dare you!
- 欢迎回来，先生  - 塞巴斯蒂安
- Welcome home, sir.  - Sebastian.
- 亲爱的  - 很高兴见到你，泽塞曼夫人
- My dear!  - Nice to have you here, Mrs Sesemann.
- 爸爸  - 克拉拉，我的孩子
- Father!  - Klara, my child.
- 我亲爱的孩子  - 太好了，爸爸
- My darling child!  - How wonderful, father.
啊，你是我们的艾迪尔海德？
Ah, so this is our Adelheid?
日安
Good day.
我有个惊喜给你
I have a surprise for you.
- 奶奶  - 克拉拉
- Grandmama!  - Klara.
我的乖乖孙女
My sweet, sweet girl.
我只是路过，但我必须见见你
I'm only passing through,but I had to see you.
让我看看你
Let me look at you.
你看起来很好
You look very well!
而且
And...
日安，夫人
Good day, medeme.
夫人
Madame.
瞎说
Poppycock!
叫我奶奶
Just call me Grandmama.
我们幸运能找到一个克拉拉的朋友
We were right to find a friend for Klara.
她好多了，很开心
She's much better, so cheerful.
恐怕我的消息会让你失望
I'm afraid my news will dampen your spirits somewhat.
在我看来，艾迪尔海德表现的…
In my opinion, Adelheid shows signs of...
我没有办法教育好她
There's no other way for me to put it...
她有点不对劲
...not being in her right mind.
不对劲
Not in her right mind?
- 什么意思  - 她不会朗读
- What do you mean?  - Adelheid still can't read.
她甚至不认识字母
She can't even recognise the letters,
即使教书先生尽他所能
even though Mr Kandidat is doing the very best he can.
这严重影响了克拉拉小姐的学习
This is seriously disrupting Miss Klara's lessons.
她的行为是不合适的，相当狂野
And her behaviour is impossible,downright wild.
好吧，我得拿个主意了
Well, well.I'm going to make up my own mind.
然后我们要对此负责
And then we'll take it from there.
当年轻的牧羊人在晚上数他的羊时
"When the young shepherd counted his sheep in the evening,
他发现最小的不见了
he realised that the smallest one was missing."
去哪了呢？
"Where could it be?"
外面开始下雪，刮起了寒风
"Outside it began to snow and an icy wind blew."
我和皮特曾今遇到过这样的情况
That happened to me and Peter once.
我们丢失了一只山羊
We lost a goat.
- 后来找到了吗？ - 是的，谢天谢地
- Did you find it again?  - Yes. Thankfully.
你从哪来
There, where you come from...
我想一定和这里不同，我说的对吗？
I'm sure it's very different to here.Am I right?
故事接下来怎么了
How does the story continue?
请告诉我
Please.
天越来越黑，雪花夹杂在空气中
"It got darker and darker and the snowflakes whirled through the air."
但是突然
"But all of a sudden
他听到了小羊的微弱心跳
he heard the very quiet bleating of a little sheep."
好吧，我就读到这儿
Right, that's where I'm stopping.
但是小羊，他找到了吗？
But the little sheep. Does he find it?
你可以自己读这一段
You can read that for yourself.
但我不会啊
But I can't.
为什么不会呢
Why ever not?
皮特说我们不需要朗读
Peter said we don't have to read.
皮特说的，是吗？
Peter did, did he?
你不能总是相信别人说的话
You don't always have to believe what other people say.
如果你能够阅读，你会知道故事接下来的情节
If you could read you would know how the story continues.
然后你会喜欢上这个故事，不是吗？
And you like stories, don't you?
是的
Yes.
那么，这样
Well, then.
这本书我留给你
I'll leave the book there for you.
海蒂是一个可爱并且极其敏感的孩子
Heidi is a sweet and incredibly sensitive child.
我相信如果给予正确的引导她会学会阅读
I'm sure she can learn to read if given the right attention.
太好了
Thank goodness for that.
但是我想她的内心并不快乐
But I get the impression that she's not very happy.
她应有尽有
She has all she could want.
是内心深处的一些东西
It's something deep inside.
住在这间屋子有违她的本性
Living in this house goes against everything she is.
克拉拉从没有这么快乐
Klara has never been so happy.
我知道
I see.
同时它也让你对独自留下克拉拉不再感到愧疚
And it stops you feeling guilty about leaving Klara alone.
胡说
Poppycock.
嗯？
Hello?
蒂妮特
Tinette.
你在做什么，手里拿的什么
What are you doing?What's in your hand?
有鬼，听到了吗？
A ghost! Don't you hear it?
- 没有鬼这玩意  - 有，听
- There's no such thing as ghosts.  - There is! Listen.
塞巴斯蒂安？救命啊，有鬼
Sebastian? Help! A ghost!
没丢东西吧
Nothing was stolen?
我亲自检查了银器三次
I checked the silver myself three times over.
我锁了门
And I locked the door.
我确定
I promise.
肯定是鬼
It was a ghost, definitely.
胡说，蒂妮特，荒唐
Poppycock, Tinette. What rot!
塞巴斯蒂安，你是个聪明人，你肯定有答案
Sebastian, you're a sensible man. You must have an explanation.
好吧，我必须承认
Well, I have to admit
如果是主人问我
that if Sir is asking me,
可以肯定的说事情发生的
then it certainly has to be said that things are happening,
嗯
that, well...
怎么说呢
that are somewhat, how shall I put it,
事情变得有点灵异
that appear somewhat supernatural.
- 灵异？ - 是的
- Supernatural?  - Yes.
好吧，接下来
Right, then.
嗯
Well...
我会制止这些愚蠢的行动
I'm going to put a stop to all these carryings-on.
不要让孩子们听到任何关于这件事的消息
Please make sure that the children hear nothing about this.
晚安
Goodnight.
- 睡觉吧  - 晚安
- To bed.  - Goodnight.
在
In... the...
山
vall...
谷里
ey...
在山谷里
"In the valley."
在山谷里，有条
"In the valley, there flowed
小溪流淌着
a small stream
在澄净的水里
and in the clear water
能看到鳟鱼在游动
you could see the trout swimming."
好样的，海蒂，我就知道你办得到
Yes! Heidi, I knew you could do it.
- 我就知道  - 太好了
- I knew it.  - Superb.
谁能想得到？
Who would have thought it?
鱼多的使小河看起来银光闪闪
"The fish glittered silver,
鱼儿们嬉闹着前进
and frolicked around playfully."
在这个美丽的地方
"Here at this lov... lovely place,
牧羊人想休息一下
the shepherd wanted to rest
吃完他的午餐
and eat his midday meal."
好样的，她做到了
Yes, she can do it!
- 我太高兴了，奶奶  - 好样的，海蒂
- I'm so pleased, Grandmama.  - Bravo, bravo, Heidi!
每个孩子都能学会朗读只有有个好老师和一些耐心
Every child can learn to read with a good teacher and some patience.
海蒂，我很高心
Heidi, I'm delighted.
我们的小瑞士女孩看起来做的很好
Our little Swiss girl seems to be doing well here.
这也是为什么
And that's why...
她能够和我们待在一起
she should stay with us.
- 永远？ - 是的
- Forever?  - Yes.
是的，我的孩子，永远
Yes, my child, forever.
- 再见，母亲  - 再见
- Goodbye, Mother.  - Goodbye.
驾…
Giddy up!
你能待多久，我的朋友
How long can you stay, friend?
生意一结束我就得离开
I'll leave as soon as this business is cleared up.
今晚我希望能亲眼见到鬼魂
I hope to see the ghost for myself tonight.
我的第一次啊
It would be my first.
孩子！
Child!
你到底在干什么？
What on earth are you doing here?
不要碰她，你不应该弄醒梦游者
Don't touch her!You shouldn't wake sleepwalkers.
她快冻僵了
She's freezing cold.
能再拿条毯子来吗？
Could you bring another blanket?
地上是什么
What on earth...
给
Here.
让我们两单独待在一起
Please leave us two alone.
不要害怕，海蒂
Don't be scared, Heidi.
是我，那个医生
It's me, the doctor.
你梦到了什么
Were you dreaming?
爷爷
About Grandfather.
你哪里不舒服？
Are you in any pain?
只有这里
No, only here.
好疼
This hurts.
亲爱的孩子，你为什么存着这些面包卷
My dear child,why did you save all those bread rolls?
它们是为奶奶准备的，她不能吃硬面包
They're for Grandmother.She can't eat hard bread anymore.
你想家了，小海蒂
You miss your home, little Heidi.
来！
Come on.
这里
There, there.
会好起来的
Everything will be okay.
思乡病？
Homesick, you say?
女孩病了，她从来没有平静过
The Swiss illness.Her nerves are in quite a state.
要立刻送她回去
She must be sent home immediately.
- 不行  - 必须送她走
- She can't.  - She must!
我不能这样对克拉拉
I can't do that to Klara. Please.
尽你所能，好吗？
Do all you can, okay?
我已经给出了我的建议
I've given you my advice.
你看到了鬼魂吗？
So? Did you see the ghost?
我什么也没说
I didn't say anything.
告诉我一切，爸爸
Tell me everything, Father. Please!
克拉拉
Klara.
鬼魂
The ghost...
是我们的小海蒂
was our little Heidi.
海蒂？
-Heidi?
因为痛苦她梦游
She sleepwalks because she's suffering.
- 她需要什么  - 她的家
- What does she need?  - Her home.
所以，亲爱的，海蒂不能待在这里了
So, my dear child, Heidi cannot stay here.
但是她应该，你不能这样做
But she has to.You can't do that!
请不要这样，没有海蒂我该怎么办
Please don't! What will I do without Heidi?
- 海蒂病了，如果想治愈只能…  - 我要她留在这儿
- Heidi's illness will only be cured...  - I want her to stay here!
- 我也病了而且一直独自一人  - 克拉拉
- I'm sick and all alone too!  - Klara.
你失控了，冷静下来
You're forgetting yourself.Calm down this instant!
走吧
Just go!
去找你的爷爷和皮特，所有人，走吧
Go to your grandfather and Peter.Everyone, just leave!
蒂妮特，送我回房间
Tinette, take me to my room right away.
艾迪尔海德
Adelheid.
塞巴斯蒂安今天会送你回家
Sebastian will take you home today.
中午你会去坐火车，蒂妮特会帮你整理行李
You'll take the train at midday.Tinette will help you pack.
回爷爷家？
Home to Grandfather?
克拉拉呢？
And Klara?
克拉拉？在吗？
Klara?
克拉拉
Klara.
开门好吗
Please open the door.
谢谢
Thank you.
能把这个交给克拉拉吗？
Can you give this to Klara?
她应该来看我
She has to come and visit me.
拜托
Please.
再见
We'll see.
驾
Giddy up.
走你
Off you go!
终于又重归平静
Peace again at last.
蒂妮特，蒂妮特
Tinette! Tinette!
就叫你海蒂吧
I'll call you Heidi.
我的小海蒂
My little Heidi.
再见
Goodbye.
人们住在这儿
People live up there...
那些山，如此的压抑
Those mountains! It's so oppressive.
来！
Come here.
非常荣幸，小姐
It has been a great pleasure, miss.
- 照看好孩子  - 会的
- Look affer the child well.  - I will.
再见
Adieu!
- 看  - 这是谁？
- Hey, look!  - What is it?
她是海蒂
That's Heidi.
你好，海蒂
Hello, Heidi.
来
Come!
太好了，我要那个
Nice! I want that!
看看这些鞋子
Look at these shoes.
- 海蒂  - 皮特
- Heidi!  - Peter!
- 海蒂，我听说你住在个宫殿里  - 不是宫殿
- Heidi, I heard you lived in a palace.  - It wasn't a palace.
- 里面是什么  - 马上就知道了
- What is in there?  - Wait and see.
这些是给你的，奶奶，很多软面包
These are for you, Grandmother. Lots of soft rolls.
你回来太好了，海蒂
It's lovely you're back, Heidi.
给你的大香肠，皮特
A big sausage for you, Peter.
谢谢
Thank you.
爷爷
Grandfather!
海蒂
Heidi!
早上好，小天鹅与小熊[山羊名]
Morning, Little Swan and Little Bear.
皮特，我来了
Peter, I'm coming!
不
No!
- 给，你的一半  - 谢谢
- So, here's your half.  - Thank you.
亲爱的克拉拉
Dear Klara,
村子现在被厚厚的大雪覆盖
the village is now under thick snow.
所有东西都是白的并且闪闪发亮
Everything is white and sparkling.
我们被迫搬到村子里住
We have moved into the village
所以我可以去上学了
so that I can go to school.
在学校，男孩坐在一边，女孩们坐在另一边
At school, boys sit on one side and girls on the other.
我们的牧师比教书先生还严厉
Our pastor is much stricter than Mr Kandidat.
有时甚至会鞭笞学生
Sometimes there are even canings.
可怜的皮特nal由于迟到经常被惩罚
And poor Peter is always punished because he's always late.
现在告诉我长大后你想干什么
Now tell me what you want to be when you grow up.
牧羊人
A goatherd.
- 农民  - 农民
- A farmer.  - Farmer.
铁匠，像我父亲一样
A blacksmith. Like my father.
铁匠
Blacksmith.
我想写故事
I want to write stories.
安静
Ouiet!
我知道了
I see.
这个字母是？
What letter is this?
- “A”？ - 这是“D”
- 'A'?  - A letter 'D'!
几乎每天放学后
Almost every day after school,
我都要教皮特朗读
I try to teach poor Peter to read.
皮特，昨天刚学过啊
Oh Peter, you did this yesterday.
现在就不会了
But it's not really working.
克拉拉，我想你了
Oh Klara, I miss you so much.
我每天都在想你
I think about you every day.
请给我写信
Please write to me.
我最期待的是你能来看我
"There's nothing I wish for more than for you to come and visit me."
你的，海蒂
"Yours, Heidi."
我甚至没有说再见
I didn't even say goodbye.
我的天啊！我的天啊，是克拉拉
I don't believe it. I don't believe it. It's Klara!
皮特，皮特，皮特！
Peter, Peter, Peter!
皮特，看，是克拉拉，我最亲爱的朋友，克拉拉
Peter, look! It's Klara.My dearest friend! Klara!
- 克拉拉  - 海蒂
- Klara!  - Heidi!
- 海蒂，我太想你了  - 我也想你
- Heidi, I missed you so much.  - I missed you too.
- 奶奶  - 海蒂
- Grandmama!  - Heidi!
我的乖孩子
My dear child.
看，克拉拉的情况相当糟糕
You see, Klara was in such an awful way,
我决定带她来这里
I resolved to bring her here.
她能在这里待一段时间吗？
Do you think she could stay here for a few days?
当然，会付钱的
For a fee, of course.
克拉拉是我们的客人
Klara is our guest.
- 好的  - 确定？
- Okay.  - Sure?
海蒂
Heidi!
海蒂，你得帮我穿衣服
Heidi, you have to help me get dressed.
- 你不需要这个  - 海蒂
- You don't need this.  - Heidi!
一件也不需要
Or any of this either.
看，我也不需要它们
Look.I don't need them either.
海蒂，不要太快
Heidi, not so fast.
小熊、小天鹅[山羊名]
Little Bear, Little Swan.
它们和我想的一样
They're just like I imagined.
皮特，过来啊
Peter, come!
皮特，看，这是克拉拉
Peter, look. It's Klara.
克拉拉，这是皮特
Klara, this is Peter.
你好，百闻不如一见
Hello.I've heard so much about you.
你来吗？
Are you coming?
- 不  - 为什么，让我们和他一起去
- No.  - Why? Let's go with him.
怎么可能，你无法走路
How will that work?You can't walk.
- 皮特  - 来吧，我们走
- Peter!  - Come on, let's go.
我不会留下克拉拉独自一人
I'm not leaving Klara on her own.
- 快走  - 皮特
- Move, go!  - Peter!
他会熬过去的
He'll get over it.
我们走，动起来
We're going! Move!
海蒂，我想和你们两个一起上山去
Heidi,I'd love to go up there with you two.
快点走
Come on! Move!
走
Move!
自己回家去吧
Go home on your own.
你们这些愚蠢的山羊
You stupid bunch of goats.
走吧，一个跟一个
Come on, get a move on! Go!
- 看到了吗  - 星星在闪耀
- Did you see that?  - Yes, a shooting star.
现在让我们许愿吧
Now we can wish for something.
- 我希望…  - 不
- I wish that…  - No!
不要说出来
You're not allowed to say.
该死的
Damn!
走吧，山羊
Come on, goats!
轮椅在哪儿，海蒂，轮椅去哪了
Where is the wheelchair? Heidi, where is it?
不在这儿
It's not here.
也不在这儿
It's not here either.
它不可能这样消失
It can't just disappear.
- 爷爷，它不见了  - 什么？轮椅不见了
- Grandfather, it's not here.  - What? It's gone?
不可能，你四处找过了吗
Impossible.Did you look everywhere?
现在我得在这儿坐一整天什么也干不了
Now I have to sit here all day and can't do anything.
爷爷会想出办法的
Grandfather will think of something.
我要好好教训他一顿
He'll be getting a piece of my mind.
小熊[山羊名]
Little Bear?
谢谢你
Thank you.
待在这儿
There you go.
我知道你做了什么，小子
I know what you did, General Goatherd.
你的坏行为会受到惩罚的
Your bad conscience is probably punishment enough.
在我晚上回来前好好照看女孩们
Now look affer the girls until I come back in the evening.
懂我的意思吗？
Do you understand me?
- 我去找皮特  - 好的，去吧
- I'll go and get Peter.  - Yes, do.
出来
Come out.
不要
I don't want to.
那好吧
Then don't.
只要这儿有吃的他就会马上出来
He'll come for sure. As soon as there's food.
好美
They're beautiful.
- 就像你说的  - 看吧，你现在就在这里
- It's just like you said.  - See? And now you're here.
我去采点蓝莓
I'll fetch some blueberries.
克拉拉
Klara!
我的天啊
Holy Mother of God.
快点过来
Come over here!
来
Come on.
你行的
You can do it.
试试
Try it.
我知道你可以的
I know you can do it!
日安
Good day.
我来接我的女儿
I'm here to collect my daughter.
- 你好，阿蒙治叔叔  - 你好
- Hello Alp-Uncle.  - Hello.
母亲，你怎么能带克拉拉来这样一个地方
Mother, how could you bring Klara to a place like this?
看看
Just look at it!
这不适合生病的女孩
This is no place for a sick girl.
这间小屋，这些怪石嶙峋
This hut, these rocks everywhere.
你必须道歉，儿子
You must excuse my son.
我现在要见我的女儿，她在哪儿
I want to see my daughter right away.Where is she?
爸爸，我在这里
Father, here I am.
克拉拉
Klara.
爸爸
Father.
我的孩子
My child.
你能走路了
You're walking.
请原谅我
Please forgive me.
爸爸
Father.
- 你能走路了  - 克拉拉
- You're walking.  - Klara.
我的孩子，这是给你的礼物
This is a present for you,my dear child.
谢谢你，奶奶
Thank you, Grandmama.
里面什么也没有啊
There's nothing in it.
你得自己把它填满
Because you'll fill it up yourself.
怎么了，孩子
What's wrong, child?
- 人们嘲笑我  - 为什么呢
- Everyone laughed at me.  - Why is that?
因为我想写故事
Because I want to write stories.
是吗
Is that right?
他们鼠目寸光，海蒂
They just don't know any better, Heidi,
因为他们只知道这个村子
because they only know this village.
但是你已经见识过外面的世界了，不是吗？
But you've seen more of the world,haven't you?
如果生活中的某件事情带给你快乐
If something in life brings you joy,
你只需要去做它就行
then you simply have to do it,
不要管别人说什么
regardless of what people say.
能见到你太好了
It was so lovely to see you.
我会想你的
I'll miss you.
我也会想你的
I'll miss you too.
再见
Goodbye.
海蒂，再见
Heidi, goodbye.
再见
Adieu!